[Music]
50 million Americans suffer from
arthritis in osteoarthritis of the knee
is the most common form making it a
leading cause of disability several
inflammatory Pathways underly the onset
and progression of the disease so
various anti-inflammatory foods have
been put to the test strawberries
decrease the level circulating the blood
of an inflammatory mediator known as
tumor necrosis Factor but that doesn't
necessarily translate into clinical
Improvement for example drinking cherry
juice can lower a sign of inflammation
known as C-reactive protein but it
failed to help with the disease but wait
it says provided symptom relief yeah it
did but no better than Placebo meaning
drinking it was essentially no better
than doing nothing uh cherries may help
with another kind of arthritis called
gout but they failed when it came to
osteoarthritis same with pomegranate
jues no significant Improvement in
symptoms but then again no significant
Improvement in inflammatory mediators
either so perhaps there's no surprise
but strawberries did decrease
inflammation uh let's see if they
actually help in a randomized double
blind crossover trial and dietary
strawberries were indeed found to have a
significant analgesic effect causing a
significant decrease in pain um there
are tumor necrosis Factor inhibitor
drugs on the market now available for
the low low cost of only about
$4,000 a year for that kind of money
you'd want some really juicy side
effects and they do not disappoint like
an especially fatal lymphoma uh I think
I'll stick with the
strawberries one of the reasons we
suspected berries might help is that if
you give people the equivalent of either
a cup a day of blueberries or two cups
of have strawberries and then drip their
blood onto cells in a Petri dish you can
see a significant blending of
inflammation compared to those who got
Placebo berries and note that the
attenuation of inflammation got better
with time so apparently the longer you
eat berries the better are there any
other foods that have been tested in
this way researchers in France harvested
cartilage from knee replacement
surgeries and then exposed them to
concentrates of the blood of volunteers
who took a whopping dose of a grape seed
and Olive extract and saw a significant
drop of induced inflammation there
haven't been any human studies putting
grape seeds to the test for arthritis
but an olive extract was shown to
decrease pain and improve daily
activities and osteoarthritis suffers so
does this mean adding olive oil to one's
diet may help no because they used Freez
dried Olive vegetation water that's
basically what's left over after you
extract the oil from the olives it's all
the water soluble components in other
words it's all the stuff that's in the
olive that's missing from olive oil if
you give people actual olives a dozen
large green olives a day you can see a
before versus after drop in an
inflammatory mediator what if you look
only at the oil a systematic review and
metaanalysis on the anti-inflammatory
benefits of olive oil found there does
not appear to be any but wait what about
papers that ascribe remarkable
anti-inflammatory effects to Extra
Virgin Olive Oil here's their evidence
on
rodents in people extra virgin olive oil
may be no better than butter when it
comes to inflammation and worse than
even coconut oil so should we just stick
to olives sadly a dozen olives a day
could take up nearly half your sodium
limit for the entire day when put to the
test extra virgin olive oil did not
appear to help with fibromyalgia
symptoms either but it did work better
than canola oil and alleviating symptoms
of inflammatory bowel disease
unfortunately I couldn't find any
studies putting olive oil intake to the
test for arthritis but wait why is this
video entitled extrav virgin olive oil
for
arthritis because are you ready for this
it appears to work
topically a double blind randomized
clinical trial of topical virgin olive
oil versus a gel containing an ibuprofen
type drug for osteoarthritis of the knee
just a gram of oil with which would be
like less than a/4 teaspoon three times
a day so that would cost less than 3
cents a day and it worked topical olive
oil was significantly better than the
drug in reducing pain um the study only
lasted a month so maybe the olive oil
would have continued to work better and
better over time what about the
effectiveness of olive oil in
controlling mourning inflammatory pain
of fingers and knees among women with
rheumatoid arthritis the researchers
went all out comparing the use of
extra-virgin olive oil to just rubbing
on nothing to rubbing on that Ibuprofen
type gel and evidently the decrease in
the disease activity score in the olive
oil group beat out the others
[Music]